<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">Author and Editor Roles used in <title>The New Handbook of Syriac Literature</title>
                </title>
                <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
                <funder>The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
                <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
                <principal>David A. Michelson</principal>
                <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
                <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</editor>
                <editor role="creator" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Taxonomy conceptualization by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Taxonomy editing, implementation, and XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/documentation/author-editor-roles.xml</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
                        Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2016-05-03</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>A taxonomy of author and editor roles referenced by <title>The New Handbook of Syriac Literature</title>.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:lang="en" xml:id="author-editor-roles-taxonomy">
                    <category xml:id="claimed">
                        <gloss type="short">Claimed</gloss>
                        <gloss type="long">A person whose authorship or editing of the work has been claimed, whether by herself/himself or by others.</gloss>
                        <desc>This role indicates that the Syriaca.org editors have either not attempted or not found it possible to label the person's role 
                        with a more precise categorization. This role or its sub-roles may be used on either an <tag>author</tag> or an 
                            <tag>editor</tag> tag. Unlike using an <tag>author</tag> or <tag>editor</tag> tag without a <att>role</att> attribute, 
                            using this role or its sub-roles (except where otherwise noted) does not justify expressing the 
                            work-person relationship with the RDF properties <term ref="http://purl.org/dc/terms/creator">dct:creator</term>, 
                            <term ref="http://schema.org/creator">schema:creator</term>, <term ref="http://schema.org/author">schema:author</term>, 
                            or <term ref="http://schema.org/editor">schema:editor</term>, since the claim denoted by this role may be incorrect.
                        </desc>
                        <category xml:id="attributed">
                            <gloss type="short">Attributed</gloss>
                            <gloss type="long">A person whom others have credited at any time with the authorship or editing of a work, regardless of whether or not 
                                the person is an actual author or editor of the work.</gloss>
                            <desc>The use of this role indicates that the Syriaca.org editors either are uncertain regarding 
                                the correctness of this attribution or have not attempted to determine its correctness. An attribution determined to be false should use the 
                                <val>#incorrectly-attributed</val> role, whereas an attribution determined to be correct will not necessarily 
                                be labeled with any role. The attributed role should also be distinguished from a person whose identity was claimed
                                <term ref="#pseudo">pseudonymously</term> by the author or editor of the work himself or herself.</desc>
                            <category xml:id="incorrectly-attributed">
                                <!-- Rather than have "incorrectly-attributed", "correctly-disputed", and "incorrectly-disputed", is it better just to have separate 
                                values for #correct and #incorrect to show whether we think the role is accurate? -->
                                <gloss type="short">Incorrectly Attributed</gloss>
                                <gloss type="long">A person whom others have erroneously credited at any time with the authorship or editing of a work.</gloss>
                                <desc>This role indicates that the Syriaca.org editors consider the attribution to be definitely false. 
                                    An attribution of uncertain accuracy should use the <val>#attributed</val> role. 
                                    False attribution should also be distinguished from a person whose identity was claimed
                                    <term ref="#pseudo">pseudonymously</term> by the author or editor of the work himself or herself.</desc>
                            </category>
                        </category>
                        <category xml:id="disputed">
                            <gloss type="short">Disputed</gloss>
                            <gloss type="long">A person whose authorship or editing of the work has been significantly disputed in scholarly literature, 
                                and who may or may not actually be an author or editor of the work.</gloss>
                            <desc>The use of this role indicates that the Syriaca.org editors 
                                either are uncertain regarding which way to resolve this dispute or have not attempted to do so. This role may be used together with the 
                                role <val>#attributed</val>, meaning that a person's role may be both disputed and attributed.
                            </desc>
                            <category xml:id="correctly-disputed">
                                <gloss type="short">Correctly Disputed</gloss>
                                <gloss type="long">A person whose authorship or editing of the work has been rightly disputed in scholarly literature.</gloss>
                                <desc>The use of this role indicates that the Syriaca.org editors think the evidence weighs against this person 
                                being an author or editor of the work, but want to alert the reader to the fact that this has been debated.
                                This role may be used together with the role <val>#incorrectly-attributed</val>.
                                </desc>
                            </category>
                            <category xml:id="incorrectly-disputed">
                                <gloss type="short">Incorrectly Disputed</gloss>
                                <gloss type="long">A person whose authorship or editing of the work has been wrongly disputed in scholarly literature.</gloss>
                                <desc>The use of this role indicates that the Syriaca.org editors think the evidence weighs in favor of this person 
                                    being an author or editor of the work, but want to alert the reader to the fact that this has been debated.
                                    This role may be used together with the role <val>#attributed</val>.
                                    This role also implies that the relationship of the work [subject] to the person [object] can be expressed by
                                    the RDF properties <term ref="http://purl.org/dc/terms/creator">dct:creator</term>  
                                    and <term ref="http://schema.org/author">schema:author</term>.
                                </desc>
                            </category>
                        </category>
                        <category xml:id="pseudo">
                            <gloss type="short">Pseudonymous</gloss>
                            <gloss type="long">A person who was not the work's author or editor, but whose identity was assumed by an author or editor of the work.</gloss>
                            <desc>This should be distinguished from an <val>#attributed</val> author or editor 
                                who has been credited with the work by others.</desc>
                        </category>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="editor">
                        <gloss type="short">Editor</gloss>
                        <gloss type="long">Any kind of editor.</gloss>
                        <desc>This role does not need to be labeled explicitly, as it is implied by any <tag>editor</tag> tag that does 
                            not have a <att>role</att> attribute. This category is merely a container for more precise editorial categories. The sub-roles 
                            contained in this role should be used only with an <tag>editor</tag> tag (not with an <tag>author</tag> tag).
                            The use of this role implies that the relationship of the work (subject) to the person (object) can be expressed by
                            the RDF properties <term ref="http://purl.org/dc/terms/contributor">dct:contributor</term> 
                            and <term ref="http://schema.org/editor">schema:editor</term>, unless the sub-role definition indicates otherwise.</desc>
                        <category xml:id="creator">
                            <gloss type="short">Creator</gloss>
                            <gloss type="long">A person directly responsible for the creation of a specific document.</gloss>
                            <desc>In particular, Syriaca.org uses this role 
                            to indicate the person who created a Syriaca.org record, even if it was created on the basis of pre-existing data.
                            The use of this role implies that the relationship of the work (subject) to the person (object) can be expressed by
                            the RDF properties <term ref="http://purl.org/dc/terms/creator">dct:creator</term>, <term ref="http://schema.org/creator">schema:creator</term>, 
                                and <term ref="http://schema.org/author">schema:author</term>.</desc>
                        </category>
                        <category xml:id="general">
                            <gloss type="short">General Editor</gloss>
                            <gloss type="long">A person who has the official title of "general editor" for a work.</gloss>
                            <desc>Syriaca.org uses this role especially
                            to designate a person with editorial oversight for a Syriaca.org resource.</desc>
                        </category>
                        <category xml:id="redactor">
                            <gloss type="short">Redactor</gloss>
                            <gloss type="long">A person responsible for compiling, rearranging, abbreviating, or interpolating text in a work.</gloss>
                            <desc>The use of this role rather than its sub-roles indicates that the Syriaca.org editors are uncertain 
                                regarding the person's more precise role in relation to the work, or have not tried to determine it.</desc>
                            <category xml:id="abbreviator">
                                <gloss type="short">Abbreviator</gloss>
                                <gloss type="long">A person responsible for abbreviating the text of a work, whether by removing text or by summarizing or paraphrasing it.</gloss>
                                <desc>This role may be used alone or together with other roles to describe the activity of an editor.</desc>
                            </category>
                            <category xml:id="arranger">
                                <gloss type="short">Arranger</gloss>
                                <gloss type="long">A person responsible for rearranging or reordering the text of a work.</gloss>
                                <desc>This role may be used alone or together with other roles to describe the activity of an editor.</desc>
                            </category>
                            <category xml:id="compiler">
                                <gloss type="short">Compiler</gloss>
                                <gloss type="long">A person responsible for compiling the text of a work from multiple sources.</gloss>
                                <desc>This role may be used alone or together with other roles to describe the activity of an editor.</desc>
                            </category>
                            <category xml:id="interpolator">
                                <gloss type="short">Interpolator</gloss>
                                <gloss type="long">A person responsible for an insertion in the text of a work.</gloss>
                                <desc>This role may be used alone or together with other roles to describe the activity of an editor.</desc>
                            </category>
                        </category>
                        <category xml:id="scribe">
                            <gloss type="short">Scribe</gloss>
                            <gloss type="long">A person who copied the text of the work onto a physical object.</gloss>
                            <desc>A person with this role is specified for a work [rather than a manuscript] only when the text-bearing object is now 
                                lost or unknown.</desc>
                        </category>
                        <category xml:id="translator">
                            <gloss type="short">Translator</gloss>
                            <gloss type="long">A person responsible for rendering the text of the work into a different language.</gloss>
                            <desc>Since translation often involves other editorial activities, the Syriaca.org editors may, at their discretion, additionally label
                                this person with the <att>role</att> of <val>#redactor</val> (or one of its sub-roles), but the lack of a 
                                specified redactor role does not imply that the translator was not also a redactor. 
                                The use of this role implies that the relationship of the work (subject) to the person (object) can be expressed by 
                                the RDF property <term ref="http://schema.org/translator">schema:translator</term>.
                            </desc>
                        </category>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-05-03" who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#ngibson">CREATED: author-roles.xml</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:lang="en">
            <head>Author and Editor Roles used in <title>The New Handbook of Syriac Literature</title>
            </head>
            <p>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The New Handbook of Syriac Literature</title>
                    <ptr target="http://syriaca.org/nhsl"/>
                </bibl> 
            uses the vocabulary defined here to specify the roles of persons in relation to works. Regrettably, it is 
            not always possible for the editors to investigate the precise roles of authors or editors, especially in 
            the cases where our information is based on datasets that were contributed by external 
            scholars or projects. This means that an author's or editor's role is sometimes not designated when it 
            could be, or that it may be a generic role (such as <val>#redactor</val> or <val>#attributed</val>)
                when it could be more specific (such as <val>#abbreviator</val> or <val>#incorrectly-attributed</val>). 
            We warmly invite readers to suggest a more precise role by using the "Corrections/Additions?" button on the page 
            for the relevant work and supplying a reliable source for the information.</p> 
            
            <p>An author or editor may have multiple roles, so long as the definitions of those roles do not 
            contradict one another. Also, authors should not have roles that are reserved for editors only.</p>
            
            <p>Technical Discussion: This vocabulary defines the values allowed for the <att>role</att> attribute 
                on <tag>author</tag> and <tag>editor</tag> tags on Syriaca.org pages.
                <list>
                    <label>
                        <att>role</att> Attribute Definition and Examples</label>
                    <item>The definition for the <att>role</att> attribute in TEI-XML can be found at 
                        <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-att.naming.html#tei_att.role"/>. 
                        See also the examples for editor/@role at <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/examples-editor.html"/>.</item>
                    
                    <label>Multiple Values</label>
                    <item>Multiple values should be separated with a whitespace. Multiple values are allowed as long as 
                        their definitions are not contradictory. For example, <tag>author role="#attributed #disputed"</tag> is permissible, whereas 
                        <tag>author role="#correctly-attributed #incorrectly-attributed"</tag> is not.</item>
                    
                    <label>Editor-Only Roles</label>
                    <item>Roles in the category <val>#editor</val> should only be used on <tag>editor</tag> tags, 
                        not on <tag>author</tag> tags.</item>
                    
                    <label>RDF Properties</label>
                    <item>Relevant RDF properties are noted in this taxonomy. These are intended to give guidance for how the work-person relationship 
                        can be expressed in RDF, but they are not exact equivalents and in some cases are much more generic than the Syriaca.org 
                        roles. For Syriaca.org work records, the RDF properties for TEI <tag>author</tag> tags that do not have a <att>role</att> attribute  
                        are <term ref="http://purl.org/dc/terms/creator">dct:creator</term> and <term ref="http://schema.org/author">schema:author</term>.
                        For <tag>editor</tag> tags without a <att>role</att> attribute, the relevant properties are 
                        <term ref="http://purl.org/dc/terms/contributor">dct:contributor</term> and <term ref="http://schema.org/editor">schema:editor</term>.
                    </item>
                </list>
                <!-- Potentially, we could also tie these roles to CIDOC-CRM, but this is a bit complicated. For example,
                [E21 Person (x)] [P14 performed] [E65 Creation (y)]. 
                [E28 Conceptual Object] [P94 was created by] [E65 Creation (y)]. 
                See http://cidoc-crm.org/cidoc_core_graphical_representation/events.html -->
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>